Eastern Association for Physical Education of College Women (EAPECW) Records, 1910-1995
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Eastern Association for Physical Education of College Women records
1910-1995
1950-1992
Eastern Association for Physical Education of College Women
MS 367
27 boxes (13 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collegiate Association. Founded by various women directors of physical training from colleges in New England. Records document the history and activities of the organization, as well as the establishment and development of physical education as a profession and as an academic discipline. Materials include photographs, correspondence and memorabilia. Topics covered include the benefits of PE; the physical and mental health of students; and women in college sports.
The EAPECW had its genesis in 1910 when Amy Morris Homans, director of physical training at Wellesley College, called together women directors of physical training and heads of athletic associations in New England Colleges for an informal meeting. After four years of these gatherings, in 1915 the group officially formed as the Association of Directors of Physical Education for College Women to "discuss the problems of organization and administration of departments of physical education in colleges, and by definite cooperation, study, experiment, and research work, broaden the scope and increase the usefulness of such departments." At this time, physical education was a relatively new addition to the college curriculum and these women met to share ideas and information and collaboratively establish policies for the emerging discipline and its professionals. Membership was limited to directors of physical education in four-year accredited colleges and universities with appropriate facilities for physical education.
At annual meetings, papers and reports were presented and roundtable discussions held on a wide variety of topics to do with the administration of college departments and curriculum; status, pay, benefits, and retirement programs for physical education faculty; and various aspects of hygiene and physical and mental health including anthropometric testing of college students.
Similar associations were formed in the midwest and the west and in 1923 the regional groups voted to affiliate as the National Association of Directors of Physical Education for Women in Colleges and Universities. The EAPECW became known as the Eastern Society of that Association.
In 1941, directors of physical education in selected junior colleges were admitted to membership in the association. Physical education faculty and staff who were not department directors were permitted to join as associate members in 1946 and as full voting members in 1948. The name of the organization was changed to Eastern Association for Physical Education of College Women at that time.
With the expansion of its membership, the EAPECW entered a second stage. Now part of an established profession, the Association ran conferences that focused less on departmental organization and more on the latest trends in physical education. The Association ran a speakers bureau and job referral service through its Personnel Committee and wrote a promotional brochure to interest high school students in the profession.
The 1960s and 1970s brought many changes to physical education. Women's participation came to be considered appropriate in an ever-expanding array of sports, college physical education requirements were abandoned along with many other academic requirements, men's and women's physical education departments merged, athletics (particularly intercollegiate athletics) saw increased emphasis in the curriculum, and the passage of Title IX set the stage for full participation of women in college athletics. All of these changes meant not only many more options for women in sport, but many more organizations for women physical educators. As physical educators became more specialized, their interests and energy shifted toward more specialized organizations and EAPECW's membership declined.
After lengthy discussion and study, as well as a needs assessment survey by a professional consulting firm, the EAPECW voted to dissolve at its June 1992 meeting "in order to preserve the history and integrity of EAPECW...rather than let it fade to insignificance."
As its legacy, the EAPECW established an endowment to support the Margaret Paulding Lecture Series. The Paulding lecture is given each year at the convention of the Eastern District Association (EDA) of the American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (AAHPERD) by a woman in higher education who has made a strong contribution to the physical education profession.
The records of the EAPECW provide substantial information about the establishment and development of physical education as a profession and as an academic discipline through most of the twentieth century.
The records consist of 13 linear feet of correspondence; minutes; reports; publications; programs; membership, committee, and officer lists; memorabilia; photographs and other papers relating to the history and activities of the organization. They date from circa 1910 to 1995 with the bulk of the materials from the period between the late 1950s and 1992 when the Association voted to disband. Significant information about the organization's early years is available in the records of meetings and conferences (in Series VIII), in the files on membership eligibility (in Series V), in files of some committees (in Series VI--see especially Expectancy Standards Commmittee, Research and Studies Committee, and Test Committee), and in newsletters (in Series X). Much more detailed information about the organization's prime years and its gradual decline is available throughout the records. The decision to disband is chronicled primarily in the records of the Executive Board (Series III).
Related materials can be found in the Sophia Smith Collection in the records of the Eastern Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (EAIAW), the Massachusetts Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (MAIAW), the Physical Education Collection, and in the Smith College Archives in the Dorothy Sears Ainsworth Papers, the Senda Berenson Papers, and in the Records of the Smith College Department of Physical Education.
This collection is organized into nine series:
I. Historical Materials and Memorabilia
II. Administration
III. Executive Board
IV. Financial Records
V. Membership Records
VI. Committee Records
VII. Programs
IX. Affiliations
X. Publications
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
All material is open to research according to the rules of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The records of the EAPECW were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection between 1975 and 1995 through the efforts of Beverly J. Becker (EAPECW President in 1975), Joyce Wechsler (EAPECW President in 1992) and Sharon L. Crow (EAPECW Treasurer in 1995).
Search Terms
Physical education and training--History--20th century--Sources; Physical education for women--History--20th century--Sources; Physical education teachers--History--20th century--Sources; Physical fitness for women--History--20th century--Sources; Trade and professional associations--United States--History--Sources; Women--Health and hygiene--History--20th century--Sources; Amsden, Katherine; Eastern Association for Physical Education of College Women--History--Sources; Homans, Amy Morris; Oglesby, Carol A.; Spears, Betty Mary; Sports for women--History--20th century-Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related materials can be found in the Sophia Smith Collection in the records of the Eastern Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (EAIAW), the Massachusetts Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (MAIAW), the Physical Education Collection, and in the Smith College Archives in the Dorothy Sears Ainsworth Papers, the Senda Berenson Papers, and in the Records of the Smith College Department of Physical Education.
- Series I. HISTORICAL MATERIALS AND MEMORABILIA (1956-95), .25 linear feet.
  This series consists of historical summaries and narrative histories, memorabilia, necrology records, and information about the EAPECW's own records dating from the late 1950s to the early 1990s. The histories were produced for Association anniversaries and as regular reports to the membership of EAPECW and the National Association for Physical Education of College Women (NAPECW). The necrology records are memorial tributes and obituaries for EAPECW members. The materials are arranged with the historical materials first, followed by the memorabilia, and information about the EAPECW records.
- Series II. ADMINISTRATION (1920-84, undated), 1.25 linear feet.
  This series consists of material related to the organization and administration of the EAPECW. Included are articles of incorporation, constitutions, and by laws of the EAPECW and operating procedures for Association officers and committees; summary lists of officers and committee chairs, policies of the Association, and the Association's position statement on Title IX of the Education Act of 1972. Also included are records related to the incorporation of the EAPECW in 1969 and its certification by the Internal Revenue Service as a tax-exempt organization. Job responsibilities of officers and committee responsibilities are detailed in the Operations Books and Operating Code and Job Analysis. The bulk of the material dates from the late 1950s through the 1980s.
- Series III. EXECUTIVE BOARD (1930-93), 2.66 linear feet.
  This series consists of records created and maintained by the Executive Board including policies; rosters; meeting agendas and minutes; correspondence and reports; and a needs assessment survey of EAPECW membership commissioned by the Board in 1990. The material is arranged with general material about the Executive Board followed by meeting records, then correspondence followed by reports. The needs assessment survey constitutes the final portion of the series.
- Series IV. FINANCIAL RECORDS (1930-93), 2.66 linear feet.
  This series consists of summary budget materials and periodic financial reports arranged in chronological order. Summary budget materials are arranged chronologically and there is one folder containing blank reimbursement forms.
- Series V. MEMBERSHIP RECORDS (1924-92, undated), .5 linear feet.
  This series is primarily EAPECW membership rosters dating from 1933 to 1992. The rosters are followed by material related to eligibilty for membership dating from the 1920s to 1940 when the Association began to expand its membership beyond directors of physical education in four-year colleges. The final section of the series is a folder of blank membership application forms dating from 1946 to 1992.
- Series VI. COMMITTEE RECORDS (1920-92), 2.75 linear feet.
  This series consists primarily of committee reports both to the Executive Board and to EAPECW membership. They are arranged alphabetically by committee name. The bulk of the material dates from the late 1950s to 1992 when EAPECW disbanded. More extensive records have survived from some committees. These include the Constitution, Expectancy Standards, Honorary Membership/Merit Award, Legislation, Nominating, Personnel, Publications, Research and Studies, and Test Committees.
- Series VII. PROGRAMS (1983-95), .25 linear feet.
  This series consists of one folder on professional seminars conducted for the EAPECW by Spectrum Consultants in the mid-1980s and material on the Margaret Paulding Lecture Series.
- Series VIII. MEETINGS AND CONFERENCES (circa 1910-92), 3.75 linear feet.
  This series is divided into three sections: Annual Business Meeting, General, and Conference Tapes. The Annual Business Meeting section consists of agendas and minutes, 1939-92. The General section consists of conference and meeting programs, proceedings, mailings, and correspondence, circa 1910-92. A sampling of one year per decade of local arrangements records was retained for the period for which such records survived, the 1960s to 1990s. Conference Tapes consists of reel-to-reel and cassette tapes of significant portions of the 1958, 1959, and 1960 conferences and smaller portions of conferences in 1965, 1967, and 1990. All three sections are arranged chronologically.
- Series IX. AFFILIATIONS (1935-75, undated), .25 linear feet.
  This series consists of correspondence with a variety of associations of physical educators as well as reports to the National Association for Physical Education of College Women, EAPECW's umbrella organization. The material is arranged alphabetically by name of organization.
- Series X. PUBLICATIONS (1936-91), .5 linear feet.
  This series contains EAPECW brochures, published business report/newsletters, and general EAPECW newsletters. The materials are arranged by type and then chronologically.
- Series I. HISTORICAL MATERIALS AND MEMORABILIA
  - History of EAPECW, 1915-56, prepared by Historical Records Committee, submitted Apr 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History of EAPECW Annual Report (yearly annual histories), 1958-1981/82 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History of EAPECW (multi-year reports), 1957-62, 1957-64, 1965-69, 1970-75 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - History, 1990-92 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - History general, 1964-76 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary celebration: photographs, program highlights, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ladies Singing Ensemble songbook, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Logo and stationery, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Necrology, 1950-92 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Summary of meetings, 1915-92, including locations, membership, and attendance statistics, 1956, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sophia Smith Collection and EAPECW records: correspondence, 1957-75 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Records of EAPECW members: report on records kept by EAPECW on its members, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. ADMINISTRATION
  - Articles of incorporation and by laws, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Constitutions, 1920-69, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Incorporation and tax-exempt status, 1968-75, undated (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Cumulative lists of officers and committee chairs, 1957-92 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Policies, 1964-78 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Position statement on Title IX, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Operations book and policies, circa 1970-86 (Box 2, Folder 22-27)
  - Operating Code, Part I, general procedures, 1966-73, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Operating Code and Job Analysis
    - Executive Board, 1960-63 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - President and Past President, 1957-76 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - President Elect, 1957-75, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Vice President and Vice President Elect, 1957-86, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Secretary, 1957-71, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Treasurer, 1957-75, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Members at Large, 1961-77, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - By laws Committee, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Conference Report Chairman/Conference Proceedings Editor, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Constitution Committee, 1957-66 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Convention Site Selection Committee, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Historical Records Committee, 1956-70, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Honorary Membership Committee, 1957-85, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - International Relations/International Understanding Committee, 1950-70, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Legislation Committee, 1957-66, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Membership and Public Relations Committee, 1957-66 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Membership Committee, 1967, 1970, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Nominations Committee, 1957-81 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Personnel Committee, 1957-70, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Public Affairs Committee, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Public Relations Committee, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Publications Committee, 1960-75 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Research and Studies Committee, 1943-77 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Research Grant Selection Committee, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Series III. EXECUTIVE BOARD
  - Composition of Executive Board, 1973-74 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Policies, 1960-69 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Rosters, 1956-93 (Box 3, Folder 55-56)
  - Agendas, 1945-92 (Box 3, Folder 57-58)
  - Minutes, 1935-72 (Box 3, Folder 59-65)
  - Minutes, 1973-92, undated (Box 4, Folder 66-69)
  - Correspondence, 1947-93 (Box 4, Folder 70-73)
  - President's correspondence
    - General, 1934-67 (Box 4, Folder 74-75)
    - Conferences, 1974-90 (Box 4, Folder 76-77)
    - Executive Board meetings, spring, 1979-87 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Invitation letters, sample, 1970-81, undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Operations Book update, 1985-86 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Officers
      - President Elect, 1977-86 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      - Past President, 1984-87 (Box 5, Folder 82)
      - Vice President, 1976-87 (Box 5, Folder 83)
      - Vice President Elect, 1976-87 (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - Past Vice President, 1977-81 (Box 5, Folder 85)
      - Secretary, 1977-87, undated (Box 5, Folder 86)
      - Treasurer, 1974-87 (Box 5, Folder 87)
      - Members-at-Large, 1976-87 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Committees
      - By Laws, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 89)
      - on the Future, 1974-77 (Box 5, Folder 90)
      - Honorary Membership/Merit Award, 1970-87 (Box 5, Folder 91)
      - International Understanding, 1974-86 (Box 5, Folder 92)
      - Membership, 1976-85 (Box 5, Folder 93)
      - Nominations, 1975-87 (Box 5, Folder 94-96)
      - Public Affairs, 1976-78 (Box 6, Folder 97)
      - Publications/Newsletter, 1974-87 (Box 6, Folder 98)
      - Research and Studies, 1976-84 (Box 6, Folder 99)
      - Site Selection, 1976-86 (Box 6, Folder 100)
      - Structure and Function, 1977-78 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Secretary-Treasurer correspondence, 1930-41 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Secretary correspondence, 1981-92 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Reports
    - President, 1968-91 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Past President, 1982-90, undated (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - President Elect, 1967-90 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Vice President, 1961-91 (Box 6, Folder 107-109)
    - Past Vice President, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Vice President Elect, 1960-91 (Box 6, Folder 111-112)
    - Secretary, 1973-92 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Members-at-Large, 1970-91, undated (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Needs Assessment Survey
    - Letter of agreement with Integrated Options, Inc., 1990 (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Needs Assessment Report, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Functional Association Self-Study Tool (F.A.S.T.) Report, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Completed survey forms, A-Z, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 118-129)
- Series IV. FINANCIAL RECORDS
  - 1914-93, undated (Box 8, Folder 130-141)
  - Budgets, 1964-81 (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Reimbursement form, undated (Box 8, Folder 143)
- Series V. MEMBERSHIP RECORDS
  - Lists, 1933-54 (Box 8, Folder 144-145)
  - Lists, 1955-92 (Box 9, Folder 146-152)
  - Eligibility: correspondence, 1924-35 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Eligibility: Junior Colleges, 1935-40 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - Blanks, 1946-92, undated (Box 9, Folder 155)
- Series VI. COMMITTEE RECORDS, (1920-92); 2.75 linear feet.
  - Committee rosters, 1960-1988 (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - By Laws Committee, 1970-91 (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - Calendar/Date Problems, Ad-hoc Study Committee, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 158)
  - Composition of the Executive Board, Committee on, 1972-73 (Box 9, Folder 159)
  - Conference Planning Committee, 1954-61 (Box 9, Folder 160)
  - Constitution Committee
    - Reports, 1957-70, undated (Box 10, Folder 161)
    - Correspondence, 1951-60 (Box 10, Folder 162)
    - Constitution, By-Laws, Revisions, 1920-70, undated (Box 10, Folder 163-164)
  - Expectancy Standards Committee
    - Questionnaires and Reports, 1938-39 (Box 10, Folder 165)
    - Correspondence, 1935-40 (Box 10, Folder 166)
  - Fall Conference Report/Proceedings Committee, 1963-85, undated (Box 10, Folder 167)
  - Fellowship Program, Ad-hoc, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 168)
  - Finance, 1974-83 (Box 10, Folder 169)
  - "Fundamentals" Study Committee survey, undated (Box 10, Folder 170)
  - on Future Directions, Ad-hoc, 1988-91 (Box 10, Folder 171)
  - on the Future, 1973-76 (Box 10, Folder 172)
  - Historical Records Committee/Archivist, 1956-91 (Box 10, Folder 173)
  - Honorary Membership/Merit Award Committee
    - General, 1957-75, undated (Box 10, Folder 174)
    - Certificates, undated (Box 10, Folder 175)
    - Correspondence, 1951-89 (Box 10, Folder 176-178)
    - Correspondence, 1990-92 (Box 11, Folder 179)
    - Honorary Membership nominees, A-Z, 1971-81, undated (Box 11, Folder 180)
    - Merit Award nominees, A-Z, 1972-77, undated (Box 11, Folder 181)
    - Programs, 1973-92 (Box 11, Folder 182)
    - Recipients lists, 1973-92 (Box 11, Folder 183)
    - Honorary Members biographical material, A-Z, 1957-85, undated (Box 11, Folder 184)
    - Merit Award recipients biographical material, A-Z, 1970-83, undated (Box 11, Folder 185-186)
    - Reports, 1956-91 (Box 11, Folder 187)
    - Rosters, 1957/58, 1972-86 (Box 11, Folder 188)
  - Integrated Options Review, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 189)
  - International Relations/Understanding Committee, 1953-91, undated (Box 11, Folder 190-191)
  - Investigate American Youth Hostels Association, Committee to, 1939-40 (Box 11, Folder 192)
  - Investigating Retirement, Income, or Annuity Plans..., 1940 (Box 11, Folder 193)
  - Investigation of Reimbursement..., Committee on, 1965 report (Box 11, Folder 194)
  - Issues and Answers, 1978-79 (Box 11, Folder 195)
  - Legislation Committee
    - General, 1957-69, undated (Box 11, Folder 196)
    - Correspondence, 1952-66 (Box 11, Folder 197)
    - Correspondence, 1967-68 (Box 12, Folder 198)
    - Reports, 1955-69, undated (Box 12, Folder 199-200)
    - Legislation (Federal and State) Material, 1955-69 (Box 12, Folder 201)
  - Membership Committee, 1938-51 (Box 12, Folder 202)
  - Membership and Public Relations Commmittee, 1952-67 (Box 12, Folder 203-204)
  - Membership and Public Relations Committee: brochure, 1955-58 (Box 12, Folder 205)
  - Membership Committee, 1967-91 (Box 12, Folder 206)
  - Nominating/Nominations Committee
    - General, 1952-90, undated (Box 12, Folder 207)
    - Reports, 1954-91 (Box 13, Folder 208)
  - Personnel and Job Referral Committee
    - General, 1956-73, undated (Box 13, Folder 209)
    - Interest Questionnaire material, 1954-70, undated (Box 13, Folder 210)
    - Reports, 1954-74 (Box 13, Folder 211)
  - President's Committee on Competition, 1968-70 (Box 13, Folder 212)
  - President's Committee on Graduate Education, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 213)
  - President's Committee on the Status of Women, 1973-74 (Box 13, Folder 214)
  - President's Committee to Study Election Procedures, undated (Box 13, Folder 215)
  - President's Committee on Timing of Board Changeover, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 216)
  - the Problem of Inexperienced College Student, Committee on, undated (Box 13, Folder 217)
  - on Programs, 1950, undated (Box 13, Folder 218)
  - Public Relations/Public Affairs Committee, 1942-50, 1968-78, undated (Box 13, Folder 219)
  - Publications Committee
    - General, 1959-60 (Box 13, Folder 220)
    - Reports, 1959-83, undated (Box 13, Folder 221)
  - Recreation Leadership, Committee on, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 222)
  - Research and Studies Committee
    - Correspondence, 1943-83 (Box 13, Folder 223)
    - Committee reports, 1939-79 (Box 13, Folder 224-225)
    - Studies reports, 1926-74, undated (Box 14, Folder 226-230)
  - Research Grant Selection Committee, 1977-81 (Box 14, Folder 231)
  - on Resolutions Concerning Principles and Ideals of Physical Education, undated (Box 14, Folder 232)